Welcome, everybody. I'm Dr.
Patricia Koyman, and I'm
going to be giving you the
lecture today on scoliosis.
Here are the
session objectives.
You will be learning about
the various types and
classifications of
scoliosis. You will be
learning about the standard
radiological diagnostic
method for assessing the
severity of scoliosis.
You will be learning about
the treatment options
for scoliosis, and you
will be learning and
reviewing the treatment
outcomes for scoliosis.
scoliosis. What is scoliosis?
It is a description of a
structural alteration or
alterations that can occur
with several conditions or
it can occur idiopathically.
It is defined as a lateral
curvature of the spine
in the coronal plane,
comparing right side to left
side, and it is also usually
accompanied by rotation
of variable amounts.
Therefore, it's also known as
a roto, for rotation
rotoscoliosis since both the
coronal and the transverse
planes are often involved.
The sagittal plane
could also be
involved as well,
as we will see.
Here is a slide showing a
drawing of a scoliosis from
a posterior view. In this
example, this is a right
convex scoliosis in the
thoracic spine, and you can
see the effect of the ribs
becoming more prominent on
this right side of the
convexity versus the left side
concavity, where the ribs
are much closer together.
And we can see in this
picture of a child from a
posterior view a similar
configuration of a right
thoracic convexity in this
region and the asymmetries
with the shoulder
heights, the iliac crest
heights, and the scapulas,
a little bit of winging,
and all the asymmetries
that you can see there.
so scoliosis is defined
as lateral group curves
equal to or greater than 10
degrees when the method of
measurement is used and
those degrees of measurement
from 10 degrees or more
is in the category of
scoliosis now spinal curves
less than 10 degrees are
termed spinal asymmetry
and these curves have no
long-term clinical significance
those may fall in the
category more of the type
one group curves scoliosis
as we mentioned is named
for the side of the
convexity of the lateral
or coronal plane curve the
apical vertebra is the one
that is the most deviated
away from the midline
sagittal plane curves are
kyphotic or like or lordotic
curves and if three planes
are involved as we mentioned
earlier, there could
be a kypho for the kyphosis,
kyphoscolytic curve.
Significant deformity of
these scoliotic curves
can occur during times
of rapid growth when the
curve is most likely to
progress and it could
cause cardiopulmonary
compromise, a great concern.
Here is a cadaver dissection.
In this view, we actually
have an anterior view. You
can see the iliac crest
the pelvic bowl okay the right
femur the left femur here
lumbar spine okay so in
this view this particular
view looking from front to
back which is not typical for
scoliosis x-rays but in this
cadaver specimen this is
the right side so we have
a right lumbar convexity
here a left kind of thoracolumbar
right in there convexity
and then a little bit of
a right upper thoracic
convexity in there so there's
multiple deviations going
on in this specimen. Okay,
so we're going to review
scoliosis classifications
now. There's several ways to
classify scoliosis, including
reversibility, severity,
cause, and location.
We will go over each of
those in turn, starting
with reversibility.
So a curve can be
functional or structural.
Structural curves do not
go away with rotational
or side bending or
forward bending motions.
Functional curves, however,
do go away with those motions.
You can have the patient bend
forward until the maximal
rib hump is visible, then
ask the patient to swing
their upper body to the right
and then to the left and
look for a reduction of the
rib hump with this action.
Now, there can be changes
from a functional curve
to become more structural
over time. There could
be progressive soft tissue
shortening. There could
be body changes. There
could be disc generation.
There could be
fibrosis of ligaments
and fascia. and there
could be decreased
active and passive
range of motion.
Another classification
category is severity.
A patient could have no
scoliosis. They could
have a mild scoliosis in
the 10 to 15 degree range.
They could have a moderate
scoliosis, usually
in the 20 to 45 degree
range. In between these
two, you could simply say
it's mild to moderate.
The patient could have a
severe scoliosis, which
would be more than 50
degrees, 50 degrees or more,
and that will affect
systemic function as well. In
this zone here between
45 and 50, that could be
dually called moderately
severe. Now, when we talk
about systemic function,
greater than 50 degrees,
the curve may affect
respiratory function, so the
respiratory system, and even
larger curves, more than
75 degrees, can affect
cardiovascular function.
Another category of
classification is cause.
There are many
categories for this.
Idiopathic is the most
common. 70 to 90 percent
of all scoliotic
curves are idiopathic.
The categories within
idiopathic include infantile,
juvenile, and adolescent,
with the adolescent
idiopathic scoliosis
being the most common
that we will spend time
on today in our lecture
discussion. Other causes
can be, besides the
idiopathic category,
congenital, acquired, and
neuromuscular as general
categories to keep in mind.
So infantile idiopathic
scoliosis can possibly be
due to the supine and
slight side-lying position,
allowing gravity to cause
plastic deformation of the
immature thorax. So
ideal treatment would be
prevention by lying kids
prone. Unfortunately, that is
the opposite of the back
-to-sleep recommendations.
So treatment with
well-fitting orthoses
and casting,
especially in the early
period of skeletal
growth, can be helpful.
So there's important
differences between the early
and the late onset
scoliosis. Okay, any child
with a significant scoliosis
before age five can
develop cardiorespiratory
failure and disabling dyspnea,
so difficulty breathing.
And the reason is
that the scoliosis decreases
the available space for
growth of the lungs.
And normally, there is a
tenfold increase in the
alveoli, from infancy to four
years of age, continuing
up to age eight years.
Okay.
Moving on.
Next in the idiopathic
scoliosis category is the
juvenile idiopathic
scoliosis, and that's between
four and ten years of age.
This is more progressive
than the more common
adolescent idiopathic scoliosis
that we'll talk about
mostly in this lecture.
With less than 20
degrees, observation and
examination with the posterior
anterior x-rays every
four to six months would
be the recommendation.
And with evidence of
progression by five to
seven degrees, then
bracing would be indicated.
There's variable success
of that type of non
-operative treatment, and
one needs to be careful
about the crankshaft
phenomenon to prevent
the crankshaft phenomenon
using potentially both
anterior and posterior
fusion to avoid that.
And there's also the
subcutaneous Harrington
instrumentation. instrumentation
to decrease the amount of
short shortening so
subcutaneous versus on the bony
landmarks and average of 4
.5 centimeters shortening if
fusion is done at such a
young age in affecting the
patient's height okay now
we're moving on in the
idiopathic scoliosis category
to the adolescent or AIS
idiopathic scoliosis
adolescent idiopathic scoliosis
the most common there is a
hereditary predisposition,
and there can be many, many
causes, and there can be
an association with
hypokyphosis, so meaning more
towards a lordosis in areas
where you might expect a
kyphosis. For example, in
the thoracic region, you may
expect a kind of normal
thoracic kyphosis that would
not be present. It would be
decreased or going towards
more lordotic positioning.
A possible CNS defect,
increased calmodulin,
et cetera. The genetic
contribution is supported
by high concordance of
the incidence and
severity of scoliosis in
monozygotic twins as
compared to dizygotic twins.
And patients with AIS
often have a sibling or
a parent with scoliosis,
and genetic loci
for AIS have been mapped
to chromosomes 17 and
19, but with an unclear
inheritance pattern.
Again, focusing on adolescent
idiopathic scoliosis,
progression of this type
of scoliosis has been
shown to be associated
with girls more than boys,
premenarchal and Risser
sign of zero. We will go
over the Risser sign
related to the iliac crest
during this lecture.
Progression is also
associated more so with double
curves, more than just the
single curves. Progression
is associated with thoracic
curves, more so than the
lumbar curves, and also
severe curves are associated
with more progression.
You would want to measure
the height of the patient,
both standing and sitting.
Okay, classifications
become two congenital.
This is the second most
common after the idiopathic
category, and 75% of
these are progressive,
and they may be associated
with other congenital
defects, such as cardiac
and genital urinary.
Congenital vertebral
defects can happen, like a
hemi vertebra, a wedge
vertebra, and in the vertebra
there could be failure
of segmentation in all of
these ways, a unilateral,
bilateral, fused ribs.
All of these are possibilities
in the congenital.
There's also the
acquired classification,
And that could be something
like osteomalacia,
sciatic irritability,
psoas syndrome,
healed leg fracture that
heals longer on that
side, from a hip
prosthesis, and irradiation
and inflammation,
other acquired means.
Another classification,
this one is quite
extensive, the
neuromuscular category.
I don't expect you to
memorize all of the detailed
categories, but we'll go
over them briefly here.
But the most common causes
neuromuscularly would be
a leg length discrepancy
and neurofibromatosis.
These are more common for
neuromuscular in relation
to, say, a leg length
discrepancy. You can check,
does the curve disappear
with forward flexion or
lying down? So is it coming
from below, from the leg
length discrepancy and
not from the spine itself?
Or is it a primary
postural scoliosis?
Okay, still in the
neuromuscular category. Again, I
put FYI here. I don't
expect you to memorize these
lists where it says FYI.
These are things that you
will go over or have gone
over in other lectures. But
for this lecture, just to
have a broad overview of
the potential neuromuscular
contributions, which could
be from a neuropathy, and
any of these findings,
a cerebral palsy,
diastomatomyelia, Frederick ataxia,
all of these, suingomyelia,
tethered spinal cord,
a mesenchymal neuromuscular
origin, Any of
these, congenital
laxity, Ehlers-Danlos
syndrome, homocysteum
or Marfan syndrome.
Also in the neuromuscular
category, trauma.
Okay, was there any
extravertebral trauma,
severe burns, any
surgery, any irradiation?
Neuromuscular also,
are there any tumors,
intraspinal, vertebral
tumors, any of these
categories noted here. It's
all in the differential
diagnosis. And
then we have other
neuromuscular classifications
related to myopathy.
And it could be any
of these findings.
Hypothyroidism,
juvenile rheumatoid
arthritis, any of
these findings.
Again, I will not hold
you responsible for
all of the lists in
the last few slides.
And then miscellaneous, the
final category, achondroplasia,
Charcot-Marie-Tooth, juvenile
spinal muscle atrophy,
all of these, poliomyelitis,
Ricketts-Schoyerman
disease, which is an
exaggerated kyphosis in
the spine. That would be
in that sagittal plane.
Was there a vertebral body
infection? See, these are
things, again, broadening
your differential diagnosis.
Okay, and the final category
for classification is location.
So a double major
scoliosis is the most
frequent is thoracic
and lumbar, so
two curves, and they
are more balanced.
The crossover region,
where it's going from
thoracic to lumbar in
different directions,
right at that crossover
region, that can
be subject to more
degenerative changes.
Location, so double major.
Also, single thoracic,
that's the second most common
after the double major.
And then progressive,
it could affect
the heart and the
lungs. It can be quite
noticeable because
it's not balanced.
Next, single lumbar
scoliosis, again, third most
common. It can be associated
with some arthritic change.
And then less commonly is
a junctional thoracolumbar
scoliosis. it's a longer
curve it can overstress the
spine and lead to some
arthritic changes here's some
here's a drawing posterior
view okay and up here in
the left upper quadrant of
the drawing we have a right
thoracic of about a curve
of 70 degrees so here we
have the thoracic spine it's
convex here on the right
okay and we name it for this
we name the sclerosis for
the convexity as you
remember so right thoracic
convexity 70 they're calling
it a 72 degree curve this is
the one that's more like the
junction of thoracolumbar
a longer curve here so right
side still because it's
convex on the right and
it's going from the thoracic
spine to the lumbar spine
so they're also calling
that 70 degrees we will go
over the type of measurement
this one they're calling a
left lumbar curve and you
can see more or less
straight here in the thoracic
spine but we get to the
lumbar convex on the left side
remember if we have a curve
like that where you look
like you're going into a
cave so there's like going
into the cave. That's the
concavity. And then the
opposite side here that we
name it for is the convexity.
Okay. And last but not
least, this is that double
major, balanced curves. So
we have right thoracic and
left lumbar. It's kind of
a reverse letter S in this
right lower quadrant of the
picture drawing here. Okay.
Presentation of the scoliosis.
In children, how does
the scoliosis present?
They're often asymptomatic and
parents or the pediatrician
or sometimes the school
nurse can check between
ages 10 to 15 when there's a
lot of rapid bone growth
occurring and the asymmetry
could be notated in someone
a little older the adolescent
again they're often asymptomatic
maybe their clothing
just doesn't fit well and
you mean a parent or the
child themselves may
notice some asymmetry or a
teacher or a gym teacher the
school nurse and in adults
they could have the
presentation may be symptoms of
arthritis or a backache or
neckache headache chest pain
or organ dysfunction so
presentation the patient may
present to the pediatrician,
because again, we were
mentioning the school nurse
may have noted an abnormality
on a scoliosis school
screening. Not all schools
have that, but many do. And
so the pediatrician should
be ready to evaluate the
patient for scoliosis, whether
it's noted incidentally
or discovered through the
school screening program,
or just the parents or the
patient themselves expresses
concern about a scoliosis.
So a spinal examination
is especially important
around age 10, just before
the growth spurt of puberty.
so evaluation what are you
going to do so you want to
exclude any underlying
etiology assess the magnitude
of the curve and the risk
for progression get a history
age of onset rate of
progression any features of
pain sometimes there's
not pain any neuromuscular
complaints shortness of breath
is it affecting the organ
system yet or not at all is
there a family history of
scoliosis parents siblings
etc what is the child's
current pubertal stage when
was the onset of Menarche,
and any limb trauma history,
infection, and arthritis.
Scoliosis, again, for the
evaluation, do a careful
physical examination with
the spinal examination. So
you want to inspect their
height, and you're going to
plot that on the gender and
age-specific graph, their
stage of puberty, the Tanner
stage, and a neurologic
examination. Check normal
walking, check toe walking,
heel walking. Can they
squat deeply? Can they hop
on each leg? And check the
abdominal reflex as well.
Continuing with
the physical and
spinal examination,
check the skin.
Are there any cafe au
lait spots or axillary
freckling? Any vascular or
hypopigmented legions or
a patch of hair overlying
the spine? Checking
for all of this. Any
skin or joint laxity? Any
high arches, the pes cavus
or hammer or colatose?
Helping with your
differential diagnosis.
Again, continuing with
the evaluation, observe
how the arms are hanging
by the patient's body.
And with a posterior
view, look at the level of
the occiput, the shoulders,
the iliac crests, P-S
-I-S, P-I-I-S, posterior
superior iliac spine. P
-I-I-S would be posterior
inferior iliac spines,
two posterior landmarks
on the ilium, just lateral
to the sacrum itself,
the greater trochanters.
Okay, the measurement
of leg length.
And you can, this is an
important one, the patient
doing a forward bending
maneuver. aka also known as
the Adams forward bend test
and you're looking for a
rib hump and does that rib
hump go away or not with
side bending to the side
of the rib hump you could
actually have them do both
sides but especially as
they go to the side of the
rib hump is this functional
or is this more structural
which we had mentioned
before run your fingers
along the spinous processes
and do you notice any lower
extremity dysfunctions
okay evaluation this is um
getting back to that forward
bending test for scoliosis.
We have a drawing here
to the side. The patient
is going to stand in front
of the physician and
parallel feet bending forward
as you see in this upper
left part of the drawing,
not quite touching the
toes, but just enough so you
can stand posteriorly and
see the posterior portion
of their back and any rib
prominence, the so-called
rib hump on one side or the
other. As this patient is
side bending left, we see
more of a prominence in
that curve. We see the
dashed lines representing the
midline of the spine, and
we can see the asymmetry.
And then side
bending to the right,
there's less of a
prominence on that side.
So is there
accentuation, or is there
improvement of the
spinal curve? Functional
curves will improve
or resolve with side
bending, whereas
structural curves will not.
Okay, and evaluation,
here we have pictures
of a patient standing,
and from left to right,
we can look without
them having been bending
forward, just look at
their normal posture, And
then just bending the
head in letter B, we can
get a sense of the cervical
spine, bending forward
at the cervical spine
level, chin on their
chest, and we can check
the upper thoracic and
cervical regions. Then
partial bending forward,
again, looking in the
thoracic and lumbar spine, and
then a little bit more
full forward bent posture
while standing, still looking
at thoracic and lumbar.
This third letter C would
be maybe a little bit more
helpful for that Adams
forward bend test positioning.
We can also use something
called a scoliometer.
Okay, and it's essentially
a carpenter's level. It
measures the angle of trunk
rotation. You may see that
abbreviated in some resources
as ATR, angle of trunk
rotation. How do you use it?
The patient is forward bend,
just like we had described
here for the Adams forward
bend test. And then you run
the scoliometer along the
patient's spine from cephalad
to caudad. And if a rib
hump is present, the scoliometer
has a little ball. It
will deviate away from the
midline of the apparatus.
We're going to review
something called the Cobb
angle, and these two
measurements are not equal. So
scoliometer degrees are
not equivalent to the Cobb
angle degrees. However,
there is a general guideline,
and that is that the ATR
angle of trunk rotation
as measured by the scoliometer
of 7 degrees correlates
with a Cobb angle of
about 20 degrees. So it's
just a general approximation,
but the two, if you're
referring to an orthopedist,
which we will talk
about, you want to make
sure he or she understands
or that they understand
that you did either a
scoliometer measurement in
the office or you actually
sent your patient for some
x-rays with a Cobb angle.
Just so that everyone's
clear which study was done.
Do a careful physical
examination, use of the
scoliometer. Now, using
it, there can be operator
-dependent measurements that
can include some sources of
error, inconsistent forward
bend test performance,
inconsistent localization of
the scoliotic curves apex.
Okay, that can be a problem.
And the scoliometer degree
markings may be poorly
visualized due to the size
of the deviating ball. It
may be too large. It's hard
to see the markings, et
cetera. interradar area
that error that is for two
different people for thoracic
curves the error is about
two degrees discrepancy
and for lumbar curves about
2.2 degrees discrepancy
intra radar error that's
you yourself having error
between how you do the
measurements with this scoliometer
in thoracic curves that
was found to be at about
1.2 degrees and then lumbar
curves about 1.6 degrees
okay next moving on here's
another picture showing
this is a typical scoliometer
someone's holding it for
demonstration purposes from
the side but in fact the
physician would be standing
behind the patient in all
of these pictures but they
would block your view and
holding the right and the
left side of the edges of
the scoliometer and moving
it from cephalad to caudad
along the spine trying
to find the most deviated
segment. And you can see
there's a little black round dot
here. In this left normal
picture, the black dot is
in the middle. In this
abnormal curve picture with a
right rib hump, that would
be a right convexity, we
see the ball deviated to the
left because the scoliometer
base is lifted on this
right side, so the ball
deviates to the left. And you
look at how many scoliometer
degrees is it deviating.
We'll go over those details
soon. But that's what the
scoliometer unit looks
like. In fact, now there are
applications on smartphones
that instead of having an
actual separate scoliometer
device like this that has
been shown to be somewhat
accurate. So using a
scoliometer application on a
phone is another option as
well. So here we have the
patient in the Adams Forward
Bend test here. In this
case, this curve you see
here is a cutout for where
the midline as much as
possible of the spine is going.
and looking at the
measurements. We
talked about the
potentials for error.
Now, we're moving on
from the scoliometer
to actual radiographic
evaluation.
In radiology, there is
standardized standing
postural X-ray images
that can be obtained.
But before sending the
patient, try and treat
the patient with OMT
to get some good spinal
mobilization. Look for
any bony pathology, sacral
basin leveling, femoral
head and iliac crest
levelness, and any scoliotic
curves, the type and
severity. And we're going
to review this, the Cobb
method of the radiology
evaluation for scoliosis.
So this is done to confirm
the presence of scoliosis
and to evaluate the type,
congenital, neuromuscular,
idiopathic, and severity,
and to assess the skeletal
maturity in relation to
the risk for progression.
So the skeletal maturity,
we'll go over some of
the other tests and radiological
studies that are done
to look for that, separate
from a postural X-ray.
and here we have standardized
standing postural
x-rays images.
What are the indications?
So if you did the
scoliometer reading in the
office and you found
it to be greater than
or equal to 7 degrees,
especially in a patient
with a BMI less than
the 85th percentile,
that's when you would want
to move on to get maybe
the standard postural x
-ray images. If there is
an obvious spinal curve
and if there's a thoracic
or lumbar asymmetry seen
on physical examination in
skeletally immature children
and there's a positive
family history of
scoliosis and you want to
monitor progression in patients
who are already diagnosed
or the orthopedic
surgeon. If you are the
orthopedic surgeon for this
patient, these are all good
reasons to get the
standardized standing postural
x-ray images. How do you
want to get them? They
should be standing. Patients
should not be supine
and they should be full
length. They will be from
posterior to anterior
and lateral views. The PA
view minimizes radiation
to the breast and thyroid,
and it's as if you're
looking at the patient from
behind. So the patient's
heart is to the examiner's
left. And when we say
full length, we're
talking about from C7 to
the sacrum and iliac crust.
And it should all be exposed
on a single long film
cassette. So send the patient
to a facility where this is
done versus obtaining
suboptimal x-rays. So you'll
want to do that. And if you
don't have that in your area
where you're working,
referring to an orthopedic
surgeon. Maybe you did the
initial screening with the
scoliometer that's fine and
refer to the orthopedic who
will be managing the patient
for more specific studies.
Okay, we touched on this
just a moment ago. Do not
have the Ritty Grabs taken
in the supine position,
since this will decrease
the effect of gravity on the
spinal curves, and that will
lead to an underestimation
of the spinal curves.
So we do not want a
supine study. So what can
you do? You can look for an
air fluid level in the
stomach, and that will confirm
that the x-ray was done
in the standing position.
And then if the
patient does have
a true leg length discrepancy,
During the actual study
itself, the patient could
have an appropriate size
block or lift put under their
known shorter leg before
the procedure. And why
is this done? So that you
get the image knowing just
what is going on in the
spine and not the additional
curves from the leg length
discrepancy asymmetry.
Lateral bending films
don't need to be obtained
initially because the
operating surgeon,
And the orthopedic
surgeon may choose to get
those at a later time
as he or she or they
are planning the surgical
correction itself.
Now we're going to go through
what exactly is the Cobb
method. Here we describe in
words what it is, and then
I will show a picture to
make it even more clear. So
where the curve is in that
convexity, you find the
highest vertebra that is
inclining towards the concavity
and a line perpendicular
to that, and then a line
inferior to the border of
the lowest vertebrae inclined
towards the concavity and a
line perpendicular to that.
And at the intersection
of the two perpendicular
lines, the degrees are
measured. And here's a
picture of that drawing.
So here's a view of a curve
here. Here's the apex,
the most coronal and
deviated vertebrae from the
midline within this curve.
And we draw a line at
the top and a line at the
bottom. And then actually
here off the screen,
they meet, and they make
the same degrees as the
two 90-degree perpendiculars
that intersect here.
So that is the cob
angle off the screen, or
a quick substitute
would be the 90 degrees,
90 degrees, and the
angle right in here.
Here we have a real patient
x-ray shown here. This is
quite a large deviation.
And so, again, like in this
drawing here, the apex is
the most deviated, and then
drawing the connecting lines
out off the image, but you
can do the perpendiculars
and get that cob angle from
there. So this is both in the
thoracic and lumbar spinous.
Described here, it's a right
thoracolumbar scoliosis.
Remember, for scoliosis,
we're looking from the back
to the front in these types
of radiological x-rays.
Okay, so how do we name
this? The scoliotic curve's
location, as noted here,
is defined by that apical
vertebra, which is what
we talked about, which
is the vertebra that is
most deviated and rotated
from that midline. So if
that apical vertebra is
located anywhere between C2
to C6, we name that location
as cervical. If it happens
to be C7 or T1, those
two vertebra, then we
call that cervicothoracic.
Location, T2 to T11,
we'll call that thoracic.
Thoracolumbar, these
two vertebra, T1,
lumbar, L234, and
then lumbosacral,
L5, and below
meaning the sacrum.
So a common adolescent
idiopathic scoliosis curve
pattern, which we mentioned
before, is a double curve.
And usually it may often
be right thoracic and left
lumbar, but we have to
remember that there are many,
many curve patterns and
configurations that can happen,
as we can see in this
list here. And the patient
may have one curve, they can
have two, they could have
a small curve and then
two larger curves, almost
like three curves. It can
get very, very complicated.
And then as you get the x-rays,
differential diagnosis
is always important. Do
the x-rays suggest any
underlying congenital or
neuromuscular etiology?
Remember at the beginning
of the lecture, we had
all those neuromuscular
categories and potential
differential diagnoses.
Again, I do not expect you
to memorize all of those
lists, but just to have
that in your awareness that
those could be possibilities
when they do the x-ray.
Are there any
paraspinal masses?
Can you see a hemivertebra
or a wedged vertebra? Is
this something that's more
of a congenital finding?
Is there a vertebral lucency
or erosion of the pedicle?
So is there a bone tumor
going on? So just reviewing
the results carefully
and with the radiologist.
Okay, so another aspect of
the radiographic evaluation
is to assess the
patient's bone age and
skeletal maturity, especially
in the adolescence, and
especially with a rapidly
progressing curve. So
some ways that are specially
done are the check X
-ray of the iliac apophysis,
and we're going to go
over that. It's called
the Risser sign, and then
one could also check an X
-ray of the hand, and that
method is the Sander's
skeletal maturity staging
system that apparently
is often used these days.
Also, one could check the
x-ray of the epithesis of
the distal radius, ulna,
and the small bones of the
hand. That method is the method
of Tanner and Whitehouse.
One could also check an
x-ray of the elbow and
assess the ossification
centers in the elbow. Two
methods, the salvo-grain
method, and there's a simpler
olecranon method. But I
highlighted the two main ones
that are most often used
currently in this present
-day time, the riser side
and the sanders skeletal
maturity staging system, so
we will go over those two.
okay so for bone age and
skeletal maturity we can get
that x-ray of the iliac
apophysis and I will show you
a picture and this is called
the research sign so in
words what is that the research
sign is a visual grading
of the degree of ossification
and or fusion present
in the iliac apophysis so
we're talking about the iliac
crest this is in the pelvic
bowl region remember the
ilium on both sides the right
ilium and the left ilium
and the iliac crest and then
as the the patient is in
the adolescent age this is
not fused yet so we give
numbers. So the Risser sign
is assigned a number based
on the visual grading of the
degree of ossification or
lack of ossification and
or fusion present in that
iliac apophysis. So if there's
none, they get a score of
zero. They get a score of
one up to 25% ossification.
And then Risser one usually
occurs after peak
height velocity.
Okay. They get a two if
there's 26 to 50% ossification.
They get a number three if
it's 51 to 75, four greater
than 76%, and full bony
fusion, they get a number
five. A low risk rate means
that the patient has quite a
bit more growth remaining
and is therefore at a greater
risk. So we need this
information to see how much
risk are they at for their
scoliotic curve progression.
So here's the
picture I promised,
scoliosis risk or sign,
radiographic evaluation.
So here we have
the numbers we just
talked about. I mean,
zero would be no
ossification. That's
not on the chart.
This is a view,
this actually is a,
I believe an anterior
view in this case.
So five is showing
full ossification.
Okay, the whole iliac crest
is ossified. We can see
that there. Okay, so one,
this one's going just
over into three. So it's
a little more than the 50%
mark. So zero to 25, 26 to
50, 50 to 75, beyond 75.
So here's your one,
two, three, four, from
laterally to medially
at that iliac apophysis.
Here's a schematic
drawing. In this
case, again, here
we're using Roman
numerals. This V is
Roman numeral five.
In the other example, we
had Arabic numbers. so
5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 same
thing in Roman numerals,
here's the 5 this is the
whole iliac apophysis
fused
and then here's just the
first 25% so this one is
a Roman numeral 1 okay, but
it's the same percentages
up to 25, 25 to 50
here's Roman numeral 3,
50 to 75 Roman numeral
4, more than 75% and then
it gets over to 5, the
whole thing fused. Okay, so
that is the riser sign.
The other one that is
also very popular for
surgeons to use when they're
following their patient
for their scoliosis and
their level of skeletal
maturity is the Sanders
skeletal maturity staging
system. So the Sanders
staging system. And this
one is often preferred.
And then there's also
some studies that may
say that this Sanders
staging system may
correlate better with
the peak height velocity.
So it may predict the
progression of scoliosis better
if these are the numbers
right here, one through eight.
And this is, they just take
an x-ray of hand okay so
we have starting with
number one i have a blown up
picture of this this is
comparing sanders versus riser
so riser we talked about
already one through five this
is full ossification here
no off ossification here and
everything in between okay
so we know about riser
sign sanders so that's the
iliac crests sanders sign using
the hand it doesn't matter
which hand i believe this
hand is the left hand
because here's like the thumb
okay doesn't matter which
hand and then the sanders
stage is here okay and we have
three or less meaning that
there's substantial growth
that is remaining four to
seven there's little
remaining growth okay seven to
eight this is a mature
skeleton and then here's a blow
up of that image so here's one
so that there's substantial
growth remaining more in
these lower lower numbers
okay but as you get up
here all the way to number
eight number seven number
eight not much growth is
remaining okay so when do we
need something more than than
an x-ray or when other than
monitoring for the amount
of level of growth that the
patient has with the Visser
sign and the Sanders staging
system, sometimes there
could be an indication for
an MRI. So if a patient
has an early onset scoliosis
before the age of 10 and
it's rapidly progressing, an
MRI may be needed, or pain.
Patients don't usually
complain of pain, but if they
do have significant
complaints of pain associated
with the scoliosis, they may
also need an MRI as well.
They may also need a CAT
scan, a bone scan, to bone
tumors or an infection okay
and other indications for an
MRI can be associated
neurologic signs and symptoms
let's say a headache neck pain
the absence of an abdominal
reflex okay that one would
have checked for before
asymmetric lower extremity
atrophy we mentioned before
the pes cavus midline skin
lesions either vascular
pigmentary or a hair patch
and also an MRI may be needed
if there are abnormal findings
on the plane radiographs
is there a congenital
scoliosis? Is there an
intraspinal pathology? Is there
an increased kyphosis? Could
this also be a Scheuermann's
disease, which is a
diagnosis of an increased,
especially thoracic kyphosis?
Okay, so you have all this
information. Maybe you
did a Cobb angle x-ray
referral to your local
center if they had good
services there, or you just
did the scoliometer and
you're going to refer to
the orthopedist so that
he, she, or they can do
their own further studies.
So when do you refer.
So let's say you did the
ATR, angle of trunk rotation,
scoliometer measurement,
and let's say it was greater
than or equal to 7 degrees
in a patient and the
patient's BMI was less than
the 85th percentile, so not
in the obese category, and
say you were not able to
get a COB measurement. So
you can refer at that point.
The next category here
would be ATR, angle of trunk
rotation, scoliometer
measurement of greater than or
equal to 5 degrees in any
patient with a BMI greater
than or equal to the 85th
percentile so a patient
more in the obese category
and you were not able to get
a Cobb angle measurement
so you can refer at that
point to the orthopedist
now if you actually did send
them for a Cobb angle and
you got results through
the radiologist that the
Cobb angle is between 20 and
24 degrees in males are
pre-monograble girls age 12
to 14 yes you can refer to
the orthopedist or if the
Cobb angle was greater
than equal to 25 degrees in
any patient you can refer
to orthopedist and here's an
important caveat progression
of any cob angle of more
than five degrees in any
patient let's say you had
an initial measurement
six to eight months later
maybe you had a second
measurement and it was progressed
more than five degrees in
anyone definite referral
to the orthopedic specialist
okay continuing with
indications for referral we
mentioned this briefly before
but please be clear about
which method of measurement
was used. Was it the Cobb
angle sending them to
the radiologist for official
studies, or was it the
in-the-office scoliometer
reading? So the degree values
represent much, much
different, quite disparate
values, and they have variable
risks for progression.
And this is a caveat here.
Orthopedic referral is not
necessary for incidental
findings of a scoliosis on a
chest x-ray, which isn't
really a scoliosis because
it's so small, when the Cobb
angle measure is less than
10 degrees. Remember, scoliosis
needs to be defined by
10 degrees or more okay so
less than that no referral
needed okay moving on here
we go we did all those
evaluations now what are we
going to do about it what's
the orthopedist going to
do about it what's the teen
helping this patient going to
do together scoliosis treatment
here's a quote for you
from Socrates as it is not
proper to cure the eyes
without the head nor the head
without the body neither is
it proper to cure the body
without the soul so thank
you to Socrates we want to
remember is very important
to keep the whole person at
the center of what's going
on, and this is a young
person, so along with their
caregiver as well, working
as a team, keeping everyone's
priorities and concerns
well represented and
acknowledged during this process.
So, soliosis treatment.
So, generally, what are
the treatment options?
Observation, bracing, and
surgery. So, those are the
main options for treatment.
Physical therapy,
chiropractic treatment, and
electrical stimulation and
biofeedback by themselves,
you know, without doing the
bracing, have not, have been
shown to be ineffective.
As always, individual
patient concerns must be
considered. And in terms
of treatment in the studies
that have been done, the
terms male and female
are used to describe the
sex assigned at birth.
And sometimes the treatment
data may not apply to
transgender and gender
diverse youth who are
receiving gender affirming
hormone therapy. So I believe
that means more research
may need to be done.
Scoliosis treatment
continued. So if we include
OMT, what would our
goal be? OMT goal in the
treatment of structural
scoliosis is to optimize
function within the
existing structure, not
to straighten the curves.
So what could we do
osteopathically? So we
can do more indirect
treatment, fascial release,
soft tissue treatment,
gentle balanced ligamentous
or membranous tension.
Sometimes we have an
acronym for those, BLT and
BMT treatments and
generally to increase the
general body range of
motion. So we want to think
about all of those things
adjunctively to whatever
else the patient has as
part of their treatment
plan. We can also think
about helping the patient
with abdominal and psoas
muscle strengthening
and we can treat joint
somatic dysfunctions as well.
In addition for
adjunctive treatment,
there are some studies
by Lauren Fishman done
in New York City, this
one from 2017, this one
from 2021 where he was
treating both adolescent
idiopathic scoliosis and
degenerative scoliosis
in older older research
subjects and had some
success with two isometric
yoga-like maneuvers
so here's a conclusion
here the yoga poses showed
promise for reversing
adolescent idiopathic
scoliosis and so more research
needs to be done on that
in your cpg there are
some links for you to read
some of these studies on
your own time as well.
Other proposed adjunct
treatments, okay, would be
the SROTH Physiotherapeutic
Scoliosis-Specific Exercises
and also in your CPG,
there are links about this
approach and that more
research needs to be done.
A conclusion here that the
short-term of the SROTH
Physiotherapeutic Scoliosis
-Specific Exercises
Intervention added
to the standard care.
and provided a large
benefit as compared to
standard care alone. So
these are, again, adjunctive
options for some of
the more mild cases,
mild to moderate cases
that could be added on. And
always good to have more
research to find out about
these things. So what is
the goal with our treatment
for AIS? The goal is a
spinal curve at skeletal
maturity with a Cobb angle
of 40 degrees or less.
So if the Cobb angle at
skeletal maturity is 50 degrees
or greater, then these can
progress more so at a rate
of one degree per year after
growth ceases so here's
an example so after 30 years
let's say their curve was
was 50 degrees initially
when they reached skeletal
maturity and then 30 years
went by with a worsening at
one degree per year over
those 30 years that means
after 30 years unfortunately
there's an 80 degree plus
curve present and that can be
associated with restrictive
lung disease compromised
pulmonary function so we
have different treatment
priorities for that situation.
Okay, here's a table, a
treatment table for you
for comparison. So we
talked about the Cobb angle,
we talked about the
Risser sign, we talked
about the Sanders stage,
and then what's the
treatment recommendation.
So let's start with the
upper left part of the
table here. So if you have
a Cobb angle on the lower
end, 11 to 19 degrees,
okay,
the treatment
recommendation when
it's that mild is observation.
Now when we get to 20
degrees, 20 to 24 degrees and
the reserve sign is still
low sanders stage is still
low one to three you follow
closely okay if there's any
changes especially within
say a six to eight month
window where there's especially
five degrees or more of
a worsening then you're
moving up to the bracing
treatment as opposed to just
following at that point now
we have the 25 to 39 degrees
if you know at the first
measurement they're still
at a low reserve sign still
at a low sander stage one
to three definitely bracing
to begin with so observation
bracing surgery okay
then we get even higher 40
to 49 degrees still we're
at the appropriate um low
reserve low sanders definitely
bracing but also we now
this is the point where we
may consider surgery at
about 45 degrees or higher
okay but when we get to
greater than or equal to 50
degrees at any stage okay
that's where surgery is going
to be the main recommendation
due to those progressive
changes as we just talked
about in the other slide.
So bracing, who is
this indicated for?
This is for skeletally
immature. We
mentioned that before,
risk of zero to two,
Sander stage one to
three patients, okay?
And bracing is not indicated
for skeletally mature
patients with risk of three
or higher or Sander stage four
to eight because they have
little growth remaining.
For bracing, we need to
have the timing be just so
so that they still have
some skeletal immaturity.
And the Cobb angle is
25 to 49 at the time of
presentation or if the cob
angle progresses, we mentioned
this before, greater than
or equal to 5 degrees
in any 6 to 8-month
observation period, moving
on to bracing. This may
prevent curve progression,
potentially reducing the
need for surgery, but it
does not correct the curve
present at the time of
diagnosis. So we're trying
to prevent progression.
So treatment. It is
contraindicated if they've
reached skeletal
maturity, which we
mentioned before. Wrists
are 4 to 5, and the
ring apophysis of that
iliac crest is fused.
And it is also contraindicated
in patients with a
cob angle greater than or
equal to the 50 degrees.
We mentioned that patient's
going towards surgery.
And it's a relative
contraindication in patients with
a thoracic lordosis. There
are some researchers who
think that most patients
with scoliosis also have a
thoracic lordosis. So that's
something that maybe needs
some more detailed research
into that. So what types
of braces are there? There's
the underarm orthoses
for most curves, and this
is known as the T-L-S-O.
We have that here, T-L-S-O.
What does that stand for?
Thoracolumbar sacral orthoses.
The Boston Brace.
There's other brands or
names, Wilmington Plastic
Jacket, Charleston Brace,
the Providence Brace, and it
prevents progression of
larger curves when worn about
18 hours a day, although
the number of hours per
day has been researched in
recent times, and it may be,
for certain patients, can
have less hours per day.
The Milwaukee brace
is rarely used now.
It had originally been
recommended for 23 hours a day,
and this one has a longer
name, CTLSO. What does that
stand for? Cervico, ceraco,
lumbar, sacral, orthosis,
and that has a very uncomfortable
under chin extension,
so 50% improvement after
six months, but at fiber
follow-up, the curve was the
same as the diagnosis, So
preventing progression is
the goal. So Boston Brace,
here's a picture here that
you can see. These are made
at a brace orthotist's office
in association with the
orthopedic center where the
patient is going for their
treatment. This one is
showing the more involved
Milwaukee brace. You can see
the cervical extension here.
It looks a little bit more
uncomfortable for the patient.
This one's really just
below the shoulder level and
below. So you get a visual
of what this is involved.
So the efficacy of
bracing has mixed
results that are reported
in the literature.
There was a trial
called the BRACED,
standing an acronym,
BRACING, BR-BRACING,
in A, Adolescent
Idiopathic Scoliosis,
BRAIST trial. It was a
five-year multi-center, 20
-center's prospective randomized
trial, and they compared
bracing and observation
in skeletally immature
patients. And the cob angle
of these patients was between
25 and 40 degrees, the
typical recommended degrees.
and what did they find out?
So here are some of the
results. They found that
bracing treatment was more
effective with increased hours
of daily wear, so 23 hours,
more success, 16 hours, a
little less success, but
still successful, eight
hours, slightly less still.
In this study, they found
it was slightly more
effective in females
compared to males, and the
bracing was less effective
in overweight patients.
So it was initially
recommended to do brace wear,
wearing of the brace, for
23 hours per day in the
past, but now 18 hours per
day is often recommended.
However, the braced trial
found that wearing the
brace approximately 13
hours per day, I think in
the study it was 12.9, was
effective for many of those
patients. The exception
was that if it was a
patient at research stage
zero, they benefited from
more hours of wearing the
brace as opposed to less.
And in terms of the
research study and or
patient compliance
measurement without an actual
study going on, they
compared the percentage
of the time that the
patient was actually
wearing the brace to what
they were prescribed,
and usually it was about
65%. And adherence can
be monitored objectively
with temperature or
press-through sensors
inside the brace as well.
When can they wear the
brace? It's not only while
they're sleeping, but they
can also wear it during
sports, except for
sports where they really
can't wear it, like
swimming and gymnastics-type
sports, and they can take
the brace off for those.
Okay, and for bracing, what
is the orthotist going to do?
They're going to check for
proper fit of the brace,
also performing an in-brace
radiograph. What do you
want to look for? It's important
to have a 20% reduction
of the in-brace Cobb angle,
and that will lead to a
greater chance of success
for the bracing treatment.
How long does the bracing
treatment continue until?
Until the end of the growth
period. So for girls, that
would be about two years
after their Menarche, so
two years post Menarche, with
their grade four or five,
and boys with their grade
five, and they can either,
the orthopedist who's
monitoring the patient can just
stop completely at that
time, or there can be a
weaning down process where
instead of wearing the brace
in the daytime and the
nighttime they switch to just
nighttime usage and this
is really orthopedic
practitioner personal preference
as to how they want to work
with their patient on that
and then after the bracing
is done there'll be a six
-month follow-up and then
yearly follow-ups for a
few years the initial curve
may collapse several degrees
but then will stabilize
okay so bracing again you
want to monitor the brace
treatment every six to
eight months both clinically
and with follow-up radiographs
out of brace radiographs
are performed to check
for any curve progression.
Progression of the curve
by greater than or equal
to five degrees during any
treatment is a poor prognosis
for the efficacy of
this treatment. And then
surgery may be needed if
there's that much progression.
Moving on to surgery for
AIS. What is the primary
goal? The primary goal is
utilizing spinal fusion
for prevention of curve
progression. Okay, that's
goal number one. Okay,
the secondary goal would
be partial curve correction,
and this is frequently
achieved. The indications
are for skeletally
immature patients, and
at diagnosis, the patient
has a curve with a cob
angle of greater and or
equal to 50 degrees, which
we mentioned previously.
If the cob angle is putting
40 and 50 degrees in some
skeletally immature patients,
they may need surgery.
So around 40, between 40 to
50, sometimes 45 degrees.
There may be a gray area
there where that may be
considered. So what are the
surgical procedures that they
often use? This is the most
common, known as posterior
spinal fusion. And there
can be bone grafting and or
instrumentation that's involved.
And the instrumentation
has evolved quite a bit
from the Harrington rods.
Harrington rods are from
cephalad to caudad and their
spinal connections with
hooks. And I will show you a
picture. And that is compared
to the modern segmental
instrumentation, which now
uses hooks and screws and
wires and rods. And then with
this new modern way, this
instrumentation provides
the surgeon, orthopedic
surgeon, with more control
for positioning of the spine.
The most important
part of the surgery is
obtaining bony fusion,
and that can be done
with the autographed
or allograft donations.
And here is some pictures
showing the Harrington
rod implantation. It's an
extensive surgery, curves
greater than 45 degrees,
and we want to stop the
structural progression
before it compromises the
cardiopulmonary function.
Here we can see the whole
length of a rod here, a
Harrington rod, and here they're
showing various aspects
of the surgical device.
okay and then surgery
there are can be options
sometimes where the surgeon
may decide they want to
do posterior spinal
fusion with the anterior
spinal fusion that's not
as common but sometimes it
could be done in skeletally
immature patients with
open tri-radiate cartilages
so where are the tri
-radiate cartilages we
can see in this picture
right here we have a
colorful schematic view this
is anterior on this side
near the yellow posterior
on this side near the
red this is a view of the
left enominate, okay,
enominate, enominate, no
name, the bone with no name,
because this is all three
bones. Here's the red
is the ileum, the green is
the ischium, and the yellow
is the pubis. So there are
three bones that eventually
fuse. When they fuse, we
call this the enominate,
enominate, again, no name,
the bone with no name,
enominate. This is the
left enominate, anterior
view, posterior view. And
what do we have here? The
tri-radiate cartilage, okay,
and it's showing the blue
lines, okay, with the open
tri-radiate cartilages.
So that's when the
posterior spinal fusion with
anterior spinal fusion could
be done. And this, why it's
done, the goal would be
to prevent the so-called
crankshaft phenomenon.
And that is something that
could occur after a posterior
spinal fusion where the
anterior spine continues to
grow. And that's a problem
because that could
cause a severe alignment
deformity, both rotationally
and in the sagittal plane.
So there's, but currently
there's some evidence that
the modern segmental type of
in instrumentation obviates
or makes unnecessary the
need for the anterior
spinal fusion so here is a
picture for you showing a
letter posterior spinal
fusion of a b and c a is pre
-surgically pre-operatively
okay and remember in the spinal
scoliotic curve x-rays
we talk about this is the
left that's the the right
view looking from posterior
and so we see the curves
and then here's using the
modern segmental hooks and
screws instrumentation we get
a lot more control going
on here. And then here's a
sagittal view where they
tried to preserve some of the
normal thoracic hyposis
and normal lumbar orthosis.
Okay.
Surgery. What about the
outcomes for the surgery? 95
% of the cases have
successful fusion. So when do
the complications happen?
If there's implant failure,
failure of fusion, also
known as the pseudoarthrosis,
if there is unfortunately a
neurologic injury, if there
is an infection or blood
loss. However, intraoperative
monitoring advances have
further decreased the risk
of complications. So hopefully
that 95% becomes even
higher with more successful
surgeries as time goes by.
So there's limited evidence
regarding the primary goal
of prevention of curve
progression with the spinal
fusion procedure. The
secondary goal of coronal curve
correction had variable
results between 48 to 67%
correction with a posterior
fusion and 71 to 93 percent
within anterior spinal fusion
procedures okay post off
operatively okay for nine
to twelve months okay sports
participation is not
recommended so once the spine
is fused sports are permitted
except for collision
sports so not the football
not the rugby not the hockey
but other sports would be
okay and long-term data is
not yet available for patients
who have had the modern
segmental instrumentation
performed on them okay curve
progression so untreated
curves may continue to
progress after skeletal
maturity that occurred occurs in
most patients two-thirds of
patients they were untreated
they will progress curves
less than 30 degrees are
much less likely to progress
a 50-year follow-up show
patients had little improvement
and sorry impairment
other than back pain and
cosmetic concerns okay and
then curve progression is
so continued curves treated
with bracing and surgery so
there was no treatment now
here's bracing and surgery
treatments those can also
progress but how much
bracing treatment patients
followed for 22 years for a
long time the average coronal
curve progression was 7.9
degrees and then surgical
treatment the patients followed
for 23 years the average
coronal curve progression
of 3.5 degrees what can
we say about scoliosis and
back pain whether the scoliosis
was treated or untreated
there is a slightly
increased occurrence of
back pain in adults who had
adolescent idiopathic scoliosis
compared to controls. And
there may be a correlation
to the initial magnitude of
the curve and later back
pain complaints. And patients
with AIS treated with
bracing or surgery may also
have an increased chance of
degenerative disc changes.
What about pregnancy?
So for scoliosis and pregnancy,
there's two comparisons.
Does the scoliosis affect
the pregnancy? And does
the pregnancy affect the
scoliosis? So let's start
with one, the patient's
pregnancy will not affect the
patient's scoliotic curves
progression. So the risk of
progression of their
scoliosis is not affected by
the number of pregnancies
or the patient's age at the
time of their first pregnancy
or the curve stability.
On the other side of the
coin, the scoliotic curve
itself does not seem to affect
the outcome of the actual
pregnancy. So there's no
apparent increase in cesarean
section deliveries or
any other health concerns
during the pregnancy as
compared to controlled patients.
Okay, to summarize for this
lecture, generally in growing
patients with a flexible
20 to 30 degree curve
approximately, and they have
documented progression of
five degrees or more, orthotic
treatment is indicated.
And then the adjunctive
treatments may be included that
we talked about before. So
some physiotherapy, osteopathic
treatment, maybe, yes, no,
maybe for the isometric
yoga poses, the Schroth
approach, some strengthening,
core strengthening so as
strengthening gentle stretches
that would be the adjunctive
approaches that we
mentioned earlier and then
larger curves 30 to 40 degrees
in growing children found
upon the initial visit
orthotics right away and
then those larger curves we
mentioned surgery and then if
it's a double curve maybe the
orthotics that we had talked
about before and as noted
more than 50 degrees likely
surgery is going to be
the best option for that
patient okay thank you here's
the summary slide we did
many things but basically we
did these two things to help
you understand the various
types and classifications
of scoliosis and knowing the
standard radiological
diagnosis method for assessing
the severity of the scoliosis.
And we went through all
of the treatment options and
the outcomes and prognosis
for the scoliosis. So
hopefully you have a better
understanding of scoliosis
at this point. I appreciate
everyone participating and
listening to this lecture.
Here are the references.
These are also all listed for
you in your CPG with the
adjunctive information as
well. Here's a lecture lab
feedback form that you will
select the lecture tab for
that and again i do appreciate
your attention during
this scoliosis lecture and
i hope everyone has a
wonderful day and we'll see you
in the lectures or in the
labs soon thank you so much